<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="invisible">INVISIBLE\nAn invisible creature is impossible to see without the aid of magic or a special sense. For the purpose of hiding, the creature is heavily obscured. The creature\'s location can be detected by any noise it makes or any tracks it leaves.\n
        Attack rolls against the creature have disadvantage, and the creature\'s attack rolls have advantage.</string>

    <string name="prone">PRONE\nA prone creature\'s only movement option is to crawl, unless it stands up and thereby ends the condition.\n
        The creature has disadvantage on attack rolls.\n
        An attack roll against the creature has advantage if the attacker is within 5 feet of the creature. Otherwise, the attack roll has disadvantage.</string>

    <string name="difficult_terrain">DIFFICULT TERRAIN\nThe travel speeds given in the Travel Pace table assume relatively simple terrain: roads, open plains, or clear dungeon corridors. But adventurers often face dense forests, deep swamps, rubble-filled ruins, steep mountains, and ice-covered ground—all considered difficult terrain.\n
        You move at half speed in difficult terrain—moving 1 foot in difficult terrain costs 2 feet of speed—so you can cover only half the normal distance in a minute, an hour, or a day.</string>

    <string name="frightened">FRIGHTENED\nA frightened creature has disadvantage on ability checks and attack rolls while the source of its fear is within line of sight.\n
        The creature can\'t willingly move closer to the source of its fear.</string>

    <string name="incapacitated">INCAPACITATED\nAn incapacitated creature can\'t take actions or reactions.</string>

    <string name="poisoned">A poisoned creature has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks.</string>

    <string name="blinded">BLINDED\nA blinded creature can\'t see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.\n
        Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature\'s attack rolls have disadvantage.</string>

    <string name="Unconscious">UNCONCIOUS\nAn unconscious creature is incapacitated, can\'t move or speak, and is unaware of its surroundings.\n
        The creature drops whatever it\'s holding and falls prone.\n
        The creature automatically fails Strength and Dexterity saving throws.\n
        Attack rolls against the creature have advantage.\n
        Any attack that hits the creature is a critical hit if the attacker is within 5 feet of the creature.</string>

    <string name="blindsight">BLINDSIGHT\nA monster with blindsight can perceive its surroundings without relying on sight, within a specific radius.\n
        Creatures without eyes, such as grimlocks and gray oozes, typically have this special sense, as do creatures with echolocation or heightened senses, such as bats and true dragons.\n
        If a monster is naturally blind, it has a parenthetical note to this effect, indicating that the radius of its blindsight defines the maximum range of its perception.</string>

    <string name="truesight">TRUESIGHT\nA monster with truesight can, out to a specific range, see in normal and magical darkness, see invisible creatures and objects, automatically detect visual illusions and succeed on saving throws against them, and perceive the original form of a shapechanger or a creature that is transformed by magic. Furthermore, the monster can see into the Ethereal Plane within the same range.</string>

</resources>